A human and Codex finally complete a difficult task. Its reusable path could become a skill.
But future sessions still hit friction, while old rules and tools keep accumulating.
Codex Metabolism lets human and AI improve the layer between them. Like slime mold, it grows candidate paths from useful work;
later use brightens what works, while unsupported branches fade.
This is not model training. It is a human-approved collaboration lifecycle: capture reusable work, observe future sessions,
then decide whether a skill, safeguard, or rule should be created, repaired, kept, or archived.
Failure, explicit correction, and same-command recovery repeat across two sessions.
One zero-install review stages CREATE HARNESS plus three lifecycle decisions, and changes nothing live.
Before creating anything, it checks necessity, Codex built-ins, installed capabilities, repository assets,
and reviewed open source. If an existing path works, creation is blocked.
For this friction, the smallest reliable fix is mechanical: require the exact reviewed preflight-and-deploy sequence.
Spoofs are denied. A person reviews the evidence and diff before activation.
Two later sessions succeed. The next review returns KEEP HARNESS, VALIDATED,
and suppresses the duplicate proposal, so the same fix does not accumulate again.
Other interventions do not get a free pass. Useful skills stay; an unused skill becomes only a retirement candidate.
Archive and restore remain human decisions. Nothing is silently deleted.
Across twenty-seven synthetic cases: zero false positives and fifty percent recall.
This is a boundary test—not proof of magical learning or real-world impact.
GPT-5.6 model gpt-5.6-sol interprets bounded workflow and friction candidates; in the live replay it challenges PATCH RULE with KEEP RULE.
Deterministic gates and human approval remain authoritative. The synthetic replay demonstrates the loop—not magical improvement.
Human and Agent can learn from every session together.
Codex Metabolism helps their shared collaboration layer grow—and let go.